<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2026-002">
  <num>KL-CY-2026-002</num>
  <heading>The Public Integrity Act of 2026</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2026-02-25</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2026-02-14</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2026-002.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2026-002</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe is a sovereign nation and has been so since time immemorial; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe exercises full enjoyment of the inherent powers of government, including self-determination and autonomy over internal affairs encompassing Tribe citizens, lands, and resources; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> on April 17, 2017, qualified voters of the Tribe ratified the Kiowa Constitution as "the supreme law of the land" (herein the "Constitution"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Legislature's duties include monitoring the actions of the government, assessing the needs of the People, and making laws toward better government to address the needs of the People under <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 1 </cite>of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a) of the Constitution</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature has identified the imperative to codify into statute ethical and procedural mandates and prohibitions related to the conduct of elected officers within the Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby adopts The Public Integrity Act of 2026.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2026-002 was duly voted upon by the Legislature on February 14, 2026, at a Legislative Regular Session CVI-(106), with a vote of (5) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (2) absent, according to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus II</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE RESOLUTION – KL-CY-2026-002</strong>
    </text>
    <text><strong>Sponsors:</strong> Cole Kickingbird-DeLaune, District 4.</text>
    <text><strong>Co-Sponsors:</strong> Kyle Ataddlety, D1; Michael Primus II, D2; Timothy Satepauhoodle, D3; Tiya Rosario, D5; Ben Wolf, D6; Warren Queton, D7.</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus II</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>X</p>
              <p>out of district</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole Kickingbird-DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2026-002 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 20<sup>th</sup> day of February, 2026, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus II</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of _________, 2026.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2026.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>LEGISLATIVE OVERRIDE ORDER: KLO-CY-2026-0XX</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Legislative Order, KL-CY-2026-00X was duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2026, at a Legislative Override Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and _____ opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <section>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Short Title</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> may be cited as The Public Integrity Act of 2026.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Findings</heading>
    <text>The preservation of the honor of the offices of the Kiowa Tribe is critical to the proper functioning of government and vital to ensuring the public's confidence in decisions made by elected leaders.  Consequently, the ethics and integrity of each elected and appointed Kiowa official are imperative to the actualization of a Tribe government that prioritizes the welfare of the Cauigu people.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Conflicts of Interest</heading>
    <text>No elected or appointed official of the Kiowa Tribe (herein an "Official") may have any pecuniary interest in any matter over which they have authority.  Should a matter of pecuniary interest fall under an elected official, said official shall recuse him- or herself from any consideration or any decision related to that matter upon learning of the conflict.  A matter shall also be considered to be a conflict of interest if the matter is of direct pecuniary interest to a family member or close relative of an Official who is a spouse, parent, child, grandparent, grandchild, sibling, first cousin, or aunt, uncle, nephew, or niece in the first degree of the Official. No other family member or close relative shall create a conflict of interest for an Official.  Direct pecuniary interest shall be one where a person will receive a financial benefit, or where a company who employs a person or is owned by a person receives a financial benefit.  A conflict of interest shall not relate to any non-profit or religious entity, or membership therein.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Use of Tribal Resources</heading>
    <text>Tribe officials and employees shall be prohibited from using Tribe resources when not acting in an official capacity. The use of Tribe resources shall constitute a civil and/or criminal offense as provided by Tribe law.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Gifts and Public Favor</heading>
    <text>Tribe officials and employees shall not accept any special advantage of services or opportunities for personal gain by virtue of employment or service in public office. Tribe officials and employees shall not accept any gift, favor, or promise of future benefits for themselves in exchange for preferential treatment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.6</num>
    <heading>Removal or Impeachment</heading>
    <text>Failure to recuse in a timely fashion after becoming aware of a Conflict of Interest identified in <cite path="1.3">Section 1.3</cite>; the abuse of Tribe resources; and/or the acceptance of gifts in exchange for public favor shall constitute grounds for impeachment and consequent removal from office.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.7</num>
    <heading>Laying Out</heading>
    <text>When an elected leader is removed from office after being impeached for any reason under Kiowa Law, including without limitation for a conflict of interest, or for any reason under <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, he or she shall not be eligible to serve as an Official thereafter for a period of 4 years after the date of conviction of the impeachment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.8</num>
    <heading>Prohibition on Retaliation</heading>
    <text>When an elected official is subject to the impeachment process delineated in the Kiowa Constitution, a moratorium on terminations for any personnel directly or indirectly under their purview shall take effect from the date of publication of impeachment charges until such time as a successor is sworn into office or conviction is denied by a vote of the Legislature.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.9</num>
    <heading>Effective Date</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> shall be deemed effective as of date the resolution adopting <cite path="">this enactment</cite> is approved by the Legislature and (a) signed into law by the Chairman or (b) the expiration of the period of ten (10) calendar days allotted to the Chairman for consideration by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> following presentment of an enactment or (c) a veto override is duly approved and signed by the Speaker of the Legislature.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.10</num>
    <heading>Primacy</heading>
    <text>To the extent that there is a conflict with any preexisting laws or internal Tribe policies, regulations, or rules whether written, verbal, official, or informal, the provisions of <cite path="">this enactment</cite> shall govern.</text>
  </section>
</document>
